<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The commoners complaint: or, A dreadful warning from Newgate, to the commons of England. Presented to the honourable committees for consideration of the commoners liberties. Wherein (as in a glasse) every free-man of England may clearly behold his own imminent insufferable bondage and slavery under the Norman-prerogative men of this kingdom, represented by the present sufferings of Richard Overton; who for his just vindication of the commoners rights and freedoms against the arbitrary domination of the House of Lords, hath by them bin imprisoned these 6 months in the goal of Newgate, his wife and his brother also by them most unjustly cast into Maiden Lane prison: ... Whereunto is annexed the respective appeales of his wife, and his brother, unto the High Court of Parliament, the Commons of England assembled at Westminster.</title>
            <author>Overton, Richard, fl. 1646.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90231</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O625</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E375_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201344</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861868</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861868</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114013</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90231)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114013)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 60:E375[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The commoners complaint: or, A dreadful warning from Newgate, to the commons of England. Presented to the honourable committees for consideration of the commoners liberties. Wherein (as in a glasse) every free-man of England may clearly behold his own imminent insufferable bondage and slavery under the Norman-prerogative men of this kingdom, represented by the present sufferings of Richard Overton; who for his just vindication of the commoners rights and freedoms against the arbitrary domination of the House of Lords, hath by them bin imprisoned these 6 months in the goal of Newgate, his wife and his brother also by them most unjustly cast into Maiden Lane prison: ... Whereunto is annexed the respective appeales of his wife, and his brother, unto the High Court of Parliament, the Commons of England assembled at Westminster.</title>
                  <author>Overton, Richard, fl. 1646.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed anno Dom. 1646. [i.e. 1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated and signed at end: Feb. 1. 1647. Richard Overton.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb: 10th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Overton, Richard, fl. 1646.</term>
               <term>Freedom of the press --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Censorship --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Detention of persons --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114013:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> THE COMMONERS <hi>COMPLAINT:</hi> OR, <hi>A DREADFVL WARNING</hi> FROM <hi>Newgate, to the Commons of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>PRESENTED To the Honourable Committee for conſideration of the <hi>Commoners Liberties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein (as in a Glaſſe) every Free-man of <hi>England</hi> may clearly be hold his own imminent inſufferable bondage and ſlavery under the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-Prerogative</hi> Men of this Kingdom, repreſented by the preſent ſufferings of <hi>Richard Overton;</hi> who for his juſt Vindication of the <hi>Commoners</hi> Rights and Freedoms againſt the Arbitrary Domination of the Houſe of Lords, hath by them bin impriſoned theſe 6 Months in the Goal of Newgate, his wife and his brother alſo by them moſt unjuſtly caſt into <hi>Maidenlace</hi> priſon: And from thence, ſhe (with her tender babe of half a years age in her armes) was, for refuſing active ſubjection to their Arbytrary Orders, dragg'd moſt barbarouſly and inhumanely head-long upon the ſtones through the ſtreers in the dirt and mire (as was her husband formerly <hi>(Novemb.</hi> 3. 1646) for the ſaid cauſe) worſe then Rebels, Traytors, Thieves, or Murtherers, to the place of execution: And in that moſt contemptible and villai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous manner caſt into the moſt reproachful, infamous Goal of Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well: And their 3 ſmall children (as helpleſſe Orphans bereft of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother, Siſter and Brother) expoſed to the mercy of the wide world.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed the reſpective Appeales of his wife, and of his brother, unto the High Court of Parliament, the Commons of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> aſſembled at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iſa. 59. 14.</bibl>
               <p rend="italic">And judgment is turned backward, and juſtice ſtandeth a farre off: for Truth is fallen in the ſtreet, and Equity cannot enter.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:114013:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114013:2"/>
            <head>To his honoured friend, Col. <hi>Henrie Martin,</hi> a Member of the Houſe of Commons, and Chair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to the honourable Committee, for conſideration of the Commoners Liberties, and in him, to all the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mbers of the ſaid Committee; The humble Information &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of <hi>Richard Overton,</hi> priſoner in the infamous Goal of New-Gate; concerning the barbarous cruelties, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane practiſes of the houſe of Lord (and of their Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative-Agents) exerciſed upon himſelf, his wife, children, and whole family, ſince his legall tryall before the ſaid ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Committee.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Jam. 2 13.</bibl>
               <q>He ſhall have judgment without mercy, that hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no mercy.</q>
               <bibl>Pſalm. 41. 1, 2.</bibl>
               <q>Bleſſed is he that conſidereth the poore, the Lord will deliver him in the time of trouble, the Lord will preſerve him, and keep him alive, and he ſhall be bleſſed upon the Earth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>Maſter Chair man,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndage and Liberty are two contraries, ſo you cannot truly conſider the one, but you muſt reflect your eye upon the other: For, though one be ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuctive to the Being of the other, that, where the one is, the other cannot be; yet, each by other is more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently diſtinguiſhed: And looke how much the one is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114013:3"/> the other, by ſo much the other is deficient, &amp; loſeth of its Property: for, <hi>quorum unum altero latius eſt, non ſuntre anum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, I humbly conceive, that, to the conſideration of the Commoners Liberties, the uſurpations, encroachments, &amp; deſtructions thereof, fall inavoydably into like conſideration, even ſo, as the one cannot be truly conſidered without the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: If you will caſt your eye upon the glory and beauty of the one, your eare muſt be open to the cry and complaint of the other; And therefore, anſwerably, as you are by the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign power of the Land</hi> ordained and deputed for the due and grave conſideration of the Common<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs Liberties, you are by the ſame Authority alſo impowred for the rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ption of all <hi>Petitions, Informations,</hi> and <hi>Complaints</hi> of the <hi>Afflicted Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moners,</hi> touching their Birth-right, Liberties, and Freedomes, and thereof to judge, and accordingly to make Report unto the Houſe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore Sir, I ſhall preſume to preſent this honourable Committee, with the late moſt barbarous inhumanities, and Turkiſh Cruelties, by the moſt <hi>Arbytrary Tyrannicall Houſe of Lords,</hi> and their <hi>Prerogative-Butchers</hi> perpetrated upon my ſelf, upon my wife, my three ſmal children, upon my brother, and the reſt of my family, in all, conſiſting of 8 perſons, all committed and acted ſince the late legall conſideration and tryal of my cauſe before you, yet ſtill depending upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of this honourable Committee: As for their former il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal uſuapations over me, I ſhal omit their repetition, they being already made publike unto the world &amp; only acquaint you with the latter.</p>
            <p>But firſt, I ſhal preſent you with thoſe their illegal cruelties <note place="margin">See the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance, &amp; the Arrow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie.</note> which concern my ſelf (they falling firſt in order) together with the mutual paſſages concerning the ſame, betwixt their Inſtruments and me, then anſwerably I ſhal deſcend to their barbarous unheard of inhumanities (ſuch as never were acted by their <hi>Norman Progenitors,</hi> ſince the <hi>Prerogative-Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of that Norman houſe was ever laid, or ever ſince they bore the name of an Houſe of Peers) now lately upon the 6. and 8. of this inſtant <hi>Ian.</hi> 1646, moſt villainouſly perpetrated upon
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114013:3"/> my wife, children, and the reſt of my family, and commit the mutual paſſages on both ſides (faithfully pend and preſented) unto your grave and judicious conſideration, to judge impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially betwixt us: And all that I in the behalf of my ſelf, &amp; of mine, ſhall crave from this honourable Committee, is but the <hi>Benefit</hi> of what the Lord himſelf hath commanded, Lev. 19. 15. <hi>Ye ſhall do no unrighteouſneſſe in judgment, thou ſhalt not reſpect the perſon of the poor, nor honour the perſon of the mighty, but in rightouſneſſe ſhalt thou judge thy neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I be found a tranſgreſſour, then let me ſpeedily ſuffer my doome; but if I be found none, then let me have ſpeedy reliefe: I craue no favour, nor boon at your hands; it is onely juſtice which I deſire, and thats but a reaſonable ſuit; a ſuit, which of Pagans, Turks, &amp; Infidels would not be condemned, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore juſtly may be expected from you.</p>
            <p>Thus, then Sir, give me leave to acquaint you, that after my laſt departure from you in the Palace yard <hi>(Novemb.</hi> 3. 1646.) and that I was cleared from your preſence, and the preſence of my friends, and was only left in the hands of my Gaolers, my indignation and deteſtation (fore-uttered in your preſence in the <hi>inward Court of Wards)</hi> againſt the Arbytrary tyrannie and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation of the houſe of Lords over the Commoners natural &amp; legal Freedomes and Rights, and over mine in particular burſt out afreſh; and upon conſideration, whether I ſhould be ſo baſe to my Country, and to my ſelf in particular, as to yeeld theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytrary Lords, ſo much <hi>Villain-ſervice,</hi> as to become their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips <hi>Prerogative-Porter,</hi> to carry my ſelf to the ſtinking, low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, barbarous Goal of Newgate again or no; I reſolved in my ſelf, that as in heart I defied all injuſtice, cruelty, tyrannie, and oppreſſion, all arbitrary uſurpation and uſurpers whatſoever, ſo in perſon (come life, come death, come what come would) I would not be ſo treacherous to my own ſelfe, to my wife and children, and eſpecially to this Nation (the Land of my Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) in general, as perſonally to yeeld my active ſubmiſſion of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny limbe that was mine (either in ſubſtance, or in ſhew) in the leaſt, to any <hi>Arbitrary Vipers or Pests, Egyptian Grashoppers, Norman Invaders and Deſtroyers</hi> of the Commoners legal inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance and birth-right, their liberties and freedoms confirmed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114013:4"/> to them, both by divine, naturall, and humane Right: or once to <hi>ſet one leg before another in ſubjection or at endance to any of their Canibal, Canker-worm, Arbytrary Orders Warrants, Significati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their pleaſures</hi> (ſo flatly contrary to all good laws, juſtice, and equity) being as ſo many Mothes in the <hi>Royall Roabe of the State,</hi> or rather as ſo many <hi>Wild-Bores</hi> out of the Forreſt, to root up, devour, diſfrancniſe and deſtroy this Nation of all her anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent legal immunities and freedoms, root and branch; yea, and of thoſe tender Plants and Seeds of the Commoners Rights &amp; Liberties, which, in the dreadfull face of ſo many late turbulent, tempeſtuous, impetuous G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſts of oppoſition rage, bloud-ſhed, and fury have been implanted and ſown in the oppreſſed <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-field of the State,</hi> the which for want of their own <hi>naturall</hi> Dew and Rain from the <hi>Superiour Orbe</hi> of Authority, but with-held by ſome Luciferean Angels of State, <hi>Regal, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary, Synodian Sottiſh and Scottiſh;</hi> the <hi>natural, free-Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of England</hi> have been forced to wet, moyſten, and manure the ſame with their <hi>bloud, their fleſh, and their bones,</hi> &amp;c. that thoſe tender Plants of freedome, equity and juſtice, might take root, be preſerved, ſpring up, flouriſh, and bring forth fruit, if not for themſelves, yet for their Poſterities.</p>
            <p>And upon theſe or the like conſiderations, I told my Jaylors, <q rend="margQuotes">that if they had no other Order or Warant for the remanding back of my perſon to the Goal of Newgate I would not ſet one leg before another in ſubjection thereto; but was fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, that if they would have me back to the Goale, they ſhould carry me.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But (Sir) leaſt the rarity and ſtrangeneſſe of this Act ſhould incurre yours and the Committes unjuſt cenſure and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, like as of the inconſiderate multitude, whoſe judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are guided by cuſtome, more then by reaſon; be pleaſed to conſider, that,</p>
            <p>All <hi>State-Deprivation</hi> of life, limbe, goods, liberty or free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, either is, or ſhould be, all and every particle thereof, the juſt execution of the <hi>Law executing:</hi> For in Equity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Action executing is indiviſible from the Law, and only &amp; preciſely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per thereto and not at all to the party executed: yea, though a man legally guilty of death ſhould be condemned by the ſame
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114013:4"/> legall Authority (or rather by perſons therein intruſted) <hi>to cut his own throat;</hi> yet were he in <hi>equity</hi> not <hi>bound</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, but in ſo doing ſhould be <hi>guilty</hi> of his <hi>own blood.</hi> And the Law of our Land makes no man his own Executioner, but hath provided Miniſters and Executioners, as <hi>Majors, Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riffes, Conſtable, Goalers, Hangmen,</hi> &amp;c. for that very end and purpoſe: And the Law of God leaves it as a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of all doubt and diſpute, and nature it ſelfe teaches, that no man ſhall be his own Butcher or Executioner, for in ſo doing, he ſhould ſin againſt his own fleſh, which is a thing moſt unnaturall and inhumane.</p>
            <p>But my <hi>rejection of carrying my own Body to the Goale,</hi> was no other but the refuſall to be my own Executioner thereins for though it were not of that degree of cruelty and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity to my own fleſh, as to cut my own throat; yet was it of the ſame nature and kind. And therefore if the one muſt be condemned as unjuſt, illegall and unnaturall, ſo muſt the other in its kind, ſo that as I was not bound, with my hands to cut my own throat, ſo with my feete, I was not bound to carry my ſelfe to priſon.</p>
            <p>And from hence is it (as I conceive) that the Law hath provided <hi>Portage</hi> with Carts, Sledges, or the like, for <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors to the place of Execution,</hi> that they might not any wayes (either actually or apparently) be guilty of their own Execution, a thing abhominated and abhorred of nature.</p>
            <p>But if it be objected, it is onely in <hi>Capitall matters,</hi> as of death, and the like, I anſwer, that from the equity where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that is founded, the other is neceſſarily implyed, one e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity being relative and eſſentiall unto both, and ſo need not be expreſſed in the leſſe: for by the equity and au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hority for the greater, the like is juſtified and commanded to be for the leſſe, for <hi>omne majus includit minus</hi> the leſſe is included in the greater, ſo that the equity in the greater cannot be denyed to the leſſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore, in caſe I were legally a priſoner, yet were I not bound therby to ſet one leg before another in my own exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>io<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> although there were no preciſe preſcript therfore in the letter of the law to diſcharge me therof, which needs no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther probation, yet for exemplary illuſtration: be pleaſed to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114013:5"/> conſider, that in the caſe of a Generalls Commiſſion, it is needleſſe to enjoyn him by <hi>litterall expreſſion,</hi> not to turne the mouthes of his Cannons againſt his own Souldiers, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat is ſo neceſſarily and naturally implyed, that it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to be expreſſed: &amp; as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is in the millitary, even ſo &amp; much more is it in the pollitick capacity, the millitary being but thereto ſubſervient.</p>
            <p>Yet further, though the letter of the Law ſhould enjoyn its Condemnants to be their own executioners, yet were that by its own equity condemned, nuld, and made voyd, for the letter muſt be ſubject to the equity: and look how much the letter tranſgreſſeth the equity, even ſo much it is une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, and is of no validity or force, for the Law taken from its originall reaſon and end is made a ſhell without a kernel, a ſhaddow without a ſubſtance, a Carkeſſe without life: for the equity and reaſon thereof is that which gives it a <hi>legall being and life,</hi> and makes it authoritative and binding, if this be not granted, injuſtice may be a Law, tyranny may be a Law, luſt, will, pride, covetouſneſſe, and what no? may be Lawes; for if equity be not the bounder of the Law, over the corrupt nature of man, all will fall into confuſion, and one man will devoure another.</p>
            <p>Beſides, as no man by Law may be his own Judge, ſo by the ſame reaſon no man may be his own Executioner, for as in equity it appropriateth ſole Judgement to it ſelf, ſo to it ſelfe it maketh ſole Challenge to its execution: for the contraction and unity of reaſon betwixt them may not be divided. So that in reaſon as it is bound to the one, in reaſon it is bound to provide for the other, &amp; the guilty be ſuſpended from both, and to the Law wholly made paſſive, both for Judgment and execution.</p>
            <p>But, if any, for want of preſident, ſhall condemn this Act of mine; to ſuch its proved rationally will anſwer, that reaſon hath no preſident; for, reaſon is the fountain of all juſt preſidents, and ſo uſed, granted and applyed by this very Parliament. 1 Book. declar. fol. 264. 298. 709. 726.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:114013:5"/>
            <p> And from this accuſtomary pedant vaſſalage formerly tho purſevants (and ſuch like catchpole devouring vermine) have made uſe for argument ſafe againſt thoſe which have complained of their Impriſonment to the Parliament, ſaying, <hi>they did not carry them to priſon,</hi> but, that <hi>they went into priſon;</hi> But I think I have prevented the uſe of that objection a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me.</p>
            <p>Thus Sir, if the Law impoſe no ſuch obligation upon its Subjects, then can that which is contradictory thereto ſo vaſſalage any? if the Law fetch not that within its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe and bounds, then much leſſe may that which is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thereto, which was my then preſent condition, for I was not in their hands, then under any legall warrant of the Law of the Land, but under an arbitrary order of the Houſe of Lords, directly contrary to the very Being of the Law of the Land: Therefore for me to be my own Executioner or its Executioner upon my ſelfe (for going or carrying cannot be denyed to be in a great meaſure its Execution) were to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the Law of Luſt, or Will, before the Law of the Land: to do more for that Power which is contrary to the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Law, then the very Law it ſelfe doth require in its own behalfe, and if that were not to make the Law of none effect, judge ye. To do that homage to ſuch a power which is not due to the Law (for no more is due to the Law then the Law doth require, and the Law doth require no more then its due) is to make <hi>Lust</hi> and <hi>Will</hi> predominant thereto, to make <hi>Will</hi> to take the <hi>Wall</hi> of the Law, to abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Law, and in the roome thereof to introduce an arbitrary power.</p>
            <p>And therefore as their Lordſhips in that their arbitrary capacity <hi>found Warrants,</hi> ſo ſhould their Lordſhips <hi>find Leggs</hi> to obey them, for I was reſolved, mine ſhould not be enſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to that their uſurpation to do their <hi>Arbitrary Drudgery,</hi> I would rather looſe my life, then in that kind to do them that vaſſalage: My <hi>Leggs</hi> were borne a free as the reſt of my <hi>Body,</hi> and therefore I ſcorne that <hi>Leggs, or Armes, or hands of mine</hi> ſhould do them any <hi>villeine-Service,</hi> for as I am a <hi>Freeman by Birth,</hi> ſo I am reſolved to live and dye, both in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114013:6"/> heart word and deed, in ſubſtance and in ſhew, maugre the Arbitrary mallice of the Houſe of Lords: yea if ought elſe I can deviſe to ſhew my actuall enmity and defiance againſt their arbitrary power, I'le do it, though it coſt the life of me, and myne, and therefore I care not who lets them know, that, that Act of mine was done in deſpite and defiance of their Warrant.</p>
            <p>But in caſe you object, that I knew well enough, that if I would not go, they would carrie me, therefore it had been better for me to have gone, then to have expoſed my ſelfe to their cruelty.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If I had known they would have hanged me, muſt I therefore have hanged my ſelfe?</p>
            <p n="2">2. A good conſcience had rather run the hazard of cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty then to abate an haires bredth of conteſtation and oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt illegality, injuſtice, and tyranny.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If they had had any legall juſtifiction over my leggs, then at their Commands my leggs were bound to obey: And then (in that caſe) I confeſſe it had been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to obey, then to have expoſed m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perſon to the cruelty of threatning mercileſſe Goalers: But being free from their Juriſdiction <hi>from the Crowne of my head to the Soale of my foote,</hi> I know no reaſon, why I ſhould <hi>foote it for them,</hi> or in the leaſt dance any attendance to their <hi>Arbitrary Warrants;</hi> their Lordſhips may <hi>put up their pipes,</hi> except they will play to the <hi>good old tune of the Law of the Land,</hi> otherwiſe their Orders and Warrants are never like to have the Service of my leggs or feet, for they were never bred to tread in their <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Steps,</hi> but I ſhall leave <hi>their Orders</hi> and <hi>their execution to themſelves.</hi> And therefore, Sir, concerning that action of mine, I ſhall continue in the ſaid eſteeme thereof, till my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence be made voide, and it be legally proved, that by the Law of the Land, <hi>I</hi> was bound to ſet one legge before an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in attendance to that Order.</p>
            <p>And further touching this matter, <hi>I</hi> deſire you to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that in the inward Court of Wards, when <hi>I</hi> diſcovered thoſe reſolutions, in the Audience of divers Gentlemen there
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114013:6"/> preſent, unto you, <hi>I</hi> told you, that <hi>I</hi> was no longer under the Arbitrary power of that illegall warrant of the Lords, but <hi>under the power of the Houſe of Commons,</hi> from which <hi>I</hi> was reſolved not to depart, which in ſome meaſure you ſeemed to oppoſe, whereat I demanded of you, <hi>How then I came there? And if I were not brought thither bp vertue of an Order from that Committee? So that though being formerly Commanded by the Lords Order to be kept in the Cuſtody of Newgate till their pleaſures ſhould be further ſignifyed, whereof to that time there had been no further ſignification at all, yet notwithſtanding I was brought from thence by vertue of an Order from that Committee, contrary to the end and intent of that Order of the Lords, ſo that I conceived, &amp; ſtill do conceive than though that Warrant were not void of it ſelfe, yet were it made voide by that Order of their own, under the power and protection of which Order I was, ſothat being there, I would not depart from the roofe &amp; verge of your Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> and this you know was the ſubſtance of my words, and thereupon indeed, <hi>I ſate we downs in the window,</hi> and told my Goaler, (but one at that time being preſent) <hi>that if he would have me to priſon, he ſhould carry me:</hi> notwithſtanding you would give him no further charge of me, for conceiving from the equity of the Law (which though contradicted by the letter is abſolutely binding and valid) that I could not be remanded back unto priſon without a <hi>new Commitment,</hi> I dema<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ded of you, <hi>if you would commit me?</hi> and I told you, <hi>that if you would, I then would goo,</hi> but that you plainly deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with an abſolute <hi>No,</hi> then I asked you <hi>if you would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand me to go and I would,</hi> but that you alſo denyed, then I told you, that <hi>if you would but intreate me for formallity ſake, (without any relation to that Order of the Lords) to go, I would go, but if you would neither commit, command, nor intreat me, then I would not go,</hi> nothing then being againſt me for my impriſonment, but that Order of the Lords, And as I was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved I told you, <hi>that I would not obey it to ſet one leg before another after its humour.</hi> Therefore Sir, how you can blame me, either of illegality or ſo much as of diſreſpect unto you, or this Honourable Committee I cannot ſee, for no Law
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114013:7"/> did I break, and to prevent all miſconſtructions I offered you more, then by Law I needed to have done.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>Had there been the letter of the Law directly againſt me, yet if it were contradicted by the equity of the Law, I had not been at all bound thereunto, except to oppoſe it: for the Letter if it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troll and over throw the equity, it is to be controlled and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne it ſelfe, upon perill of treaſon to the equity, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity to be preſerved as the thing onely legally obligatory and binding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But (Sir) there was neither letter nor equity of the Law againſt me, but that which was directly contrary to both: for the Lords warrant was directly oppugnant and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive both to the legall letter and equity.</p>
               <p>Therefore (Sir) I conceive that I was in no meaſure bound thereunto, but was as free legally, as in caſe that warrant of the Lords never had been. So that I had good cauſe, in caſe you would have had me part with my liberty, to demand, if that you would <hi>commit me, command me, or entreate me,</hi> and upon your denyall of all theſe to tell you, that then I would not go: For do you think that I am ſuch a foole to part with my liberty, for nothing? Sir, our liberties have been bought at a dearer rate, then ſo to be trifled and ſlighted away, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to captivate the ſame to the exhorbitant wills of the Lords, and to caſt my ſelfe in priſon during their boundleſſe pleaſures.</p>
               <p>Had you committed me, commanded me, or entreated me; and thereupon I had gone, and been caught in my own net, yet had <hi>I</hi> been delivered from a worſe, <hi>and of two evills the leſſe is to be choſen,</hi> for thereby the pretended power of the Houſe of Lords over me (even in its very formality) had been utterly routed; and my ſelfe abſolutely cleared from their prerogative Bondage. But at that time you were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded to do it, but left me to their Lordſhips Arbytrary power.</p>
               <p>But now Sir, I would not have you think from theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of mine, that I would be ſubject to an arbitrary pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er more in you then in the other, for truly in thoſe demands
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114013:7"/> there was tacitly couched a ſuppoſition of that which I knew could not be granted, and therefore I was the freer in my propoſall thereof, having an aſſurance that they would never be granted, yet I thought I would make tryall, but and if I had been impriſoned thereon, after I had given their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips that <hi>Fob,</hi> you ſhould have heard from me with a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; for I cannot ſuffer oppreſſion and be ſilent.</p>
               <p>Sir excuſe my prolixity about this matter, for by reaſon of the rarity and the common condemnation thereof, I have therefore the more enlarged my ſelfe, for the better removall of all ſcruple thereon. Now Sir I ſhall further acquaint you with the mutuall proceedings betwixt the Goalers and me, and judge indifferently and impartially betwixt us.</p>
               <p>Thus Sir, as <hi>I</hi> have told you, having declared my ſet reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to my attendant Goalers, away <hi>I</hi> was borne to the Boate, and when I was landed at <hi>Black-Fryers,</hi> they would have forced me along up the hill on my feete, yea, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated me, but at that time I was not minded to be their <hi>DRVDG,</hi> or to make uſe of my feet to carry the reſt of my body to the Goale, therefore I let them hang as if they had been none of my own, or like a couple of farthin Candles dangling at my knees, and after they had dragged me in that admire-able poſture a while, the one took me very reverently by the head, and the other as reverently by the feete, as if he had intended to have done Homage to His Holineſſes great Toe, and ſo they carried me: but truly Sir, I laughed at the conceit in my ſleeve. But this their reverend uſage did not continue long, for they grew rerie irreverend and deboyſt of a ſudden, for ever when they were a little wearie, they let my bodie fall upon the ſtones, and then againe moſt vallar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſlie like men well appointed for the Cauſe, they tooke me by the head and ſhouldiers, and juſt as if I had been a dead Dog, they drag'd and trayl'd my body upon the ſtones, and without all reverence to my cloth, drew me through the dirt and mire, and plucked me by the hair of the head, juſt as if the Iohn of all Sir Johns had got little Martin by the feathers, notwithſtanding the peoples ſeverall exclamations againſt their inhumane incivility and tyrannie towards me, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114013:8"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir ſeverall deſires to carrie me in a Chaire: And indeed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n caſe I had been legallie their priſoner, yet had they no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, to keepe me in evill cuſtodie, incivilie or inhumane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to uſe me, but were bound onely to keep me in ſafe cuſtody, and therein to uſe me like a man, and therefore in caſe they would not have ſo honoured me, as to have made me a Chairman, they might have carried me in a Porters Basket, or in a Cart, (provided it had not been Weſtward) or in ſome other ſuch decent neceſſary Toole, And in this like unheard of barbarous manner they brought me into the lower roome in <hi>Newgate;</hi> called the Lodge, and there they threw me down upon the Bords, and having Sir <hi>Edward Cookes</hi> 2. part inſtit. upon <hi>Magna Charta</hi> the Mr. <hi>Briſcoe</hi> offered to wreſt it out of my hands: Then I demanded of him if he intended to <hi>rob</hi> me, and he told me he would have it from me whether I would or no.</p>
               <p>To whom I replyed, that he ſhould not, if to the utmoſt of my power I could preſerve it from him, and I would do my utmoſt, where upon I clapped it in my Armes, and I laid my ſelfe upon my belly, but by force, they violently turned me upon my back then <hi>Briſcoe</hi> (juſt as if he had been ſtaving off a Dog from the Beare) ſmote me with his fiſt, to make me let go my hold, whereupon as loud as I could, I cryed out, murther, murther, murther. And thus by an aſſault they got the great Charter of <hi>Englands Liberties and Freedoms</hi> from me; which I laboured to the utmoſt of power in me, to preſerve and defend, and ever to the death ſhall maintain, and forth with without any warrant poore <hi>Magna Charta</hi> was clapt up cloſe priſoner in <hi>Newgate,</hi> and my poore fellow priſoner derived of the comfortable viſitation of friends: And thus being ſtript of my armour of proofe, the Charter of my legall Rights, Freedoms, and Liberties, after the aforeſaid barbarous manner they hurried me up into the common Goale, and as they carried me up ſtaires, as their cuſtome is, when they bring in a fellon, they gave 3. knocks at the door, and ſo they caſt me into that Goale as a fellon, and then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would be ſure I ſhould have a paire of prerogative
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114013:8"/> letters, they clapt 2. great Irons with a Chaine betwixt them upon my leggs, and Ile aſſure you, Sir, me thought they were the comlyeſt gingling Spurres that ever I wore in my life, and if your worſhip will be but pleaſed to travell with me to the Land of Liberty, come but and take horſe at <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> and you ſhall be furniſhed Ile warrant you, after the gallan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt manner, and if need be for the conduct, we ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> raiſe up the Trained Bands of <hi>Newgate,</hi> even thouſands, and ten thouſands of lice to guard you: which indeed and in truth may too ſoone be the generall portion of all the beſt Members in the Houſe, if you be not active, vigulant, and faithfull to your friends.</p>
               <p>And in thoſe Irons I continued that night and till the next day at evening, and then <hi>Woleſton</hi> the vice Maſter Goaler of <hi>Newgate</hi> ſent to me by one of his ſubſtitute Goalers, the Turn-key, to ſpeake with me below, to whom I returned this anſwer, go tell your maſter that I do not owe him ſo much ſervice, as to come downe to him to ſpeak with him in Irons, he knowes well enough where I am, if he have any buſineſſe with me let him come and ſpeak with me, and he came againe, and againe, with the like meſſage; and I returned the ſame an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: in the meane time one of his underling Goalers asked me if I would pay for my Irons, and then they ſhould be knocked off, but I told him, I neither ſet him a work to knock them on, neither would I ſet him a work to knock them off, and he that ſets you a work let him pay you your wages, for you ſhall not have a farthen of me, then departing and as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, acquainting <hi>Woelſton</hi> therewith, he returned againe with his hammer in his hand, and told me, he muſt knock them off, and ſo he did. And when I came down to <hi>Woleſton,</hi> he would needs have made me believe, that I ſent to ſpeake with him, and to deſire him to take off my Irons, and to be removed to the Maſters ſide againe; but I told him no ſuch matters, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that was farre from me, in thought, word, or deed: for I ſcorne to crouch or debaſe my Spirits to the lawleſſe cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of any mercileſſe tyrants or Goalers whatſoever: they may devoure my Carkaſe, and make that bend and break with their cruelty, but I truſt in God, that in heart and action to the umoſt of my power in the purſuance of juſtice and truth,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114013:9"/> I ſhall bid defiance to the laſt gaſpe of breath to all their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions and tyrannios whatſoever.</p>
               <p>Now Sir, having diſcovered their oppreſſions and grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt me, I ſhall now make bold to preſent this honorable Committee with the ſalvage and barbarous inhumanity exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon my Wife, and upon the reſt of my Family: Thus then be pleaſed further to conſider, that thoſe <hi>Norman Prerogative-Invaders,</hi> have not been herewith content thus to rob me in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular of my juſt liberty and freedome, and for theſe ſix mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nths to incarcerate and corrode my perſon in their prerogative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devouring jawes of <hi>Newgate,</hi> but to fil up the meaſure of their iniquity againſt me, they ſend forth their <hi>Blood-hounds,</hi> the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops old Catch-poles, the Maſter and Wardens of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>Stationers,</hi> to ſurprize my wife and my brother, and to bring them up to their <hi>Prerogative-Barre,</hi> who for refuſing to be intangled and enſlaved to their <hi>High-Commiſſion Star-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-bondage</hi> of catching <hi>Interrogatories,</hi> were both upon the ſixth of this inſtant <hi>January</hi> 1646. committed by them to <hi>Mayden-lane-priſon.</hi> But being not therewith content, the next day, without all remorſe or compaſſion over my helpleſſe children, juſt as if they had intended to deſtroy me root and branch, they ſend forth their Catch-poles again to my houſe to fetch away my <hi>Brother-in-law,</hi> and my ſiſter (his wife) which, for their preſent neceſſity, were forced to live with me, and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remained for the over-ſight, ordering and tendance of my three children in the abſence of their Father and Mother. But he being out of the way; &amp; ſhe by the great mercy of God, eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping their hands, (through their ignorance of her face) fled, &amp; hid her ſelfe, and ſome adjacent neighbours (touched with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion and pitty over the poore, afflicted, deſtitute, helpleſſe children) took them, for the preſent, into their houſes; and ſo, <hi>Father, Mother, Children,</hi> and <hi>All,</hi> being <hi>driven out of Houſe and home,</hi> the <hi>Doores were ſhut up;</hi> and I, and mine, expoſed to utter ruine and confuſion by thoſe inſulting, domineering, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Uſurpers and Tyrants, <hi>The Houſe of Lords.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here, their moſt inhumane, tyrannicall deſires not cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, out of the boundleſſe limits of their orbitrary domination, they <hi>iſſue</hi> forth yet another prerogative order againſt my wife, not counting it miſerable and diſhonourable enough, that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114013:9"/> ſhe ſhould lye in the Goale at <hi>Mayden-lane,</hi> but, as much as in them lyes, for ever to obliterate the honour of her <hi>modeſty, civility,</hi> and <hi>chaſtity;</hi> they order, that ſhe ſhall be caſt into the moſt infamous Goale of <hi>Bride-well,</hi> that common Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre and receptacle of bauds, whores, and ſtrumpets, more fit for their wanton retrograde Ladies, then for one, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet could be taxed of immodeſty, <hi>either in countenance, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, words, or action.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, this order being brought to her by the City Marſhall to command her away to <hi>Bride-well,</hi> ſhe thereupon refuſed (as by Law ſhe was bound, as hath been proved before this Honourable Committee in the caſe of Lieut: Coll. <hi>Iohn Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne,</hi> and of mine) to yeeld in the leaſt manner any ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or obedience thereto, but to the utmoſt teſtimony of her weake power made oppoſition and reſiſtance againſt it, for in plain down-right termes (like a true bred Engliſh wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man brought up at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel)</hi> ſhe told the Marſhall that ſhe would not obey it, neither would ſhe ſtir after it, ſo much as to ſet one legg before another in attendance thereto: yet, Sir, this rejection and contempt here of the Lords uſurped juriſdiction was not uttered without all due reſpect and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of your indubitable Authority, for ſhe told him, <hi>that if he brought any Order or Warrant from the Houſe of Commons, ſhe would freely and willingly yeeld all humble obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſubjection thereto,</hi> which was as abſolute an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of her acknowledgment and ſubmiſſion unto <hi>Englands</hi> legitimate lawfull authority as the other was of defiance and contempt to all arbitrary uſurpation whatſoever.</p>
               <p>Now the Gentleman Goaler hearing her reſolution and honeſt intentions for the freedoms of her Country, that rather then ſhe would yeeld any ſubjection or connivence to the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary uſurpations of any, how great or powerfull ſoever, ſhe would expoſe her ſelfe to the mercileſſe cruelty of the whole Houſe of Norman-prerogative tyrants, I ſay no ſooner had this <hi>Turky-cock Marſhall</hi> heard of her uprightneſſe to the Commons of England, but up he briſled his feathers and looked as bigg and as bugg as a Lord, and in the height and ſcorne of deriſion (juſt as if he had been Speaker
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114013:10"/> to the Houſe of <hi>Peers protempore)</hi> out he belched his fury and told her, that <hi>if ſhe would not go, then ſhe ſhould be carried in a Porters Baſket, or elſe draged at a Carts Arſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſhe modeſtly reply'd <hi>that he might do as it ſeemed good into him, for ſhe was reſolved on her courſe,</hi> but thereat his worſhip being put into a prerogative chafe; out he <hi>ſtruts</hi> in his <hi>Arbitrary Fury,</hi> as if he would have forthwith leavied whole <hi>Armies,</hi> and <hi>Droves</hi> of <hi>Porters</hi> and <hi>Carr-men,</hi> to advance the poore little harmleſſe innocent wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and her tender Babe to <hi>Bridewell:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But going (as I conceive to conſult with their Lordſhips what was beſt to be done) he upon his returne finding her conſtant to her honeſt and juſt reſolutions, our againe he flings in his wonted fury, and finding ſome of her friends at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to ſee the event of the buſineſſe, he ſhut them out of the doores and abuſed them with infamous ſcurrilous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, nicknames, and deriſions, with ſeverall menacies to impriſon them, threatning them to fetch a warrant to bring them before the now (preſent pretended illegall) Lord Mayor of <hi>London;</hi> but departing in that inſolent turbulent chafe, he ſent for a couple of Porters, but when they came to her like ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt &amp; diſcreet men, they told him, that <hi>they would not meddle with a woman that was with child, and had a young ſucking Inſant in her Armes, leaſt in ſo doing they might doe that to day which they might anſwer for to morrow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then the Marſhall thinking to bugbear them with the cracking ſound of the Houſe of Lords told them, that <hi>the Lords had ordered that ſhe ſhould be carried to Bridewell:</hi> but one of the Porters wiſely anſwered, <hi>that their Lordſhips Order was for Goalers, and not for Porters to carry her, and for their parts, they would carry no quick fleſh, if he had any dead fleſh they would carry it,</hi> and ſo they departed and left their Lordſhips preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive drudgery to their prerogative vaſſals.</p>
               <p>Then forth againe goes this their Lordſhip: furious Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion with his prerogative Commiſſion of Array, to raiſe up new Forces to encounter this weak woman, and her tender Babe on her breaſt, and having leavied a Cart for the preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Warres of the Houſe of Peers, which being brought under
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114013:10"/> the conduct of that moſt puiſſant Marſhall of <hi>London</hi> to the priſon Gate, the Car-man hearing what this beleagred wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was, wiſely refuſed to lay any hands on her, and departed in peace.</p>
               <p>Then this grim Phyliſtin of the Houſe of Peers, being thus deſerred of his forraigne forces, muſtered up his Life Guard of Goalers ſervants, or hangmen Deputies, and therewith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ſtorme her, and advancing to her Chamber doore, firſt he attempted to circumvent her by his pollicy with fair, hypocriticall, ſpecious promiſes of his and their Lordſhips favour and grace, in caſe ſhe ſhould open the doore and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit her ſelfe, but ſhe ſlighted his proffers, &amp; contemned all fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour flowing from that moſt bitter and corrupt prerogative Fountaine.</p>
               <p>Whereupon he cauſed his men to break open the doore, and entring her Chamber, ſtruts towards her like a Crow in a gutter, and with his valiant lookes like a man of mettle aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes her and her Babe, and by violence attempt to pluck the tender Babe out of her Armes, but ſhe forcibly defended it, and kept it in deſpite of his Man-hood: then he and <hi>Chriſtopher Marſhall</hi> his brother <hi>Sam: Tolſon,</hi> and divers of his ſervants by the Marſhalls Command example &amp; Authority laid violent hands upon her, and drag'd her down the ſtaires, and in that infamous barbarous manner, drew her headlong upon the ſtones in all the dirt and the mire of the ſtreetes, with the poore Infant ſtill crying and mourning in her Armes, whoſe life they ſpared not to hazard by that inhumain barbarious u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and all the way as they went, utterly to defame and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her infamous in the ſtreets, the fellowes which dragged and carried her on two Cudgels, calling her <hi>Strumpet</hi> and vild <hi>Whore,</hi> thereby to poſſeſſe the people, that ſhe was no wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of honeſt &amp; godly Converſation, whom they ſo barbarouſly abuſed, but a vile ſtrumpet or whore, and were dragging to <hi>Bridewell</hi> that common ſhore &amp; ſinke of Bauds &amp; Whores, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For no man could reaſonably imagin that any modeſt ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill woman ſhould be ſo ſhamefully uſed, eſpecially in her way to <hi>Bridewell;</hi> which diſhonourable infamous uſage was a ſufficient matter to blaſt her reputation for ever, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114013:11"/> ſuch a perpetuall odium upon her, that for the future (if ever delivered from her bondage) ſhe ſhould not paſſe the ſtreetes upon her neceſſary occaſions any more without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mely and deriſion, ſcoffing, hiſſing, and poynting at her, with ſuch or the like ſayings, as, ſee, ſee, <hi>there goes a Strum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet that was dragged through the ſtreetes to Bridewell,</hi> and this is the honour that their Lordſhips are pleaſed to conferre on the free Commoners wives who ſtand for their Freedoms and Liberties.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A Charg againſt the houſe of Lords</note>Now Sir, I humbly deſire this Honourable Committee to conſider, whether it be reaſonable or ſufferable, or any wiſe ſutable to the freedoms of the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> or to the great truſt repoſed in you, either for you to ſuffer, or for them to uſurpe ſuch an unlimited prerogative juriſdiction, to deprive husbands of their wives, and wives of their husbands; Fathers and Mothers of their Children, and Children of their Fathers and Mothers; caſt them into ſeverall infamous tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting priſons, hale and drag in moſt barbarous manner, the Commoners wives and their tender Infants upon the ſtones of the ſtreetes through all the dirt, and the mire, as if the Commoners, their wives and Children were but as dirt and mire under their Lordſhips feet, to be trod and trampled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at their pleaſure; alſo to reproach, revile, and diſhonour modeſt, chaſte, and civill women with the imputation and ſcandall of whores, ſtrumpets, &amp;c. expoſe whole families to ruine, out them out of houſe and home, and inſtead of pitty and compaſſion over ſuch tender Infants whom they have made Orphants to their Arbitrary pleaſures to turne them (without all remorſe and compunction of heart) to the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the wide world, and not in the leaſt to looke after them, take any charge or care over them, or to ſend them or their impriſoned Parents ſo much as a crum of bread, or a drop of pottage for their comfort or reliefe; but as much as in them lyes, to expoſe ſuch tender innocent babes with their parents to famin for want of ſuſtenance and reliefe, as alſo to ſend forth their armed men in an hoſtile manner, with muſquets, ſwords, piſtols, &amp;c. to beſett and aſſault the Commoners Houſes; forcibly to enter their Bed-Chambers with drawn ſwords,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114013:11"/> and piſtols ready cocked, even while ſuch perſons are in their beds alſo dayly to commit Burglary, flat fellony, break in peeces the Commoners doores, burſt open their locks, their Trunks, Cheſts, Deſkes, &amp;c. pick their pockets, ranſacke their houſes, plunder, rob, ſteale, and felloniouſly beare away their proper goods and livelyhood, as alſo to ſhutt up ſuch as are moſt faithfull for the freedoms of the Commons of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> cloſe priſoners, deprive them of the benefit of pen, ink, and paper, of the comfortable countenance and viſitation of friends, tumble and toſſe them from Goale unto Goale, lay moſt unreaſonable fines upon them, as of 2000. 1. or the like, ten times beyond the eſtate of perſons ſo fined, cenſure them to ſeven yeares impriſonment, endeavour to enforce the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moners wives, to dip their hands in the blood of their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, and to betray their friends and faithfull lovers of their Country into their mercileſſe hands, impoſe oathes upon ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to betray their Maſters Councels, and ſecrets, impriſon, fine, cenſure, and moleſt the Commoners of <hi>England,</hi> for their vindication and defence of the great Charter of their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and freedoms, for appealing from their uſurped juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to the Houſe of Com: and for refuſing to be againe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled in the Star-Chamber High-Commiſſion aboliſhed Bondage of Interrogatories and the like; as alſo for thoſe Lords to overturne the fundamentall Lawes of this Kingdom, both for liberty, property, and freedome, endeavouring the Introduction of an Arbitrary Government, and to cruſh and deſtroy all ſuch as ſhall adventure the diſcoverie of their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions or ſhall (as legally they are bound) reſiſt their arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary proceedings, ſtop all free progreſſe in the Law, commit the Compter Serjeants, and ſuch Miniſters of the Law unto priſon for arreſting their ſons or kindred for debt, and that by the authority of that Houſe, as a contempt offered thereto. All which inſufferable oppreſſions, and cruelties with mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold others, I can and will (God permitting) juſtifie and prove to their faces, if I ſhall be called thereto. And I do hereby, before this honourable Committee, and conſequently before the whole Commons of <hi>England,</hi> both repreſented and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative, Charge the Houſe of Lords (which uſually aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114013:12"/> at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> and which do arrogate unto themſelves a Parliamentarie title, and power without the free election and common conſent of the free borne people of <hi>England)</hi> with thoſe forementioned uſurpations and devaſtations of the Commoners Liberties and Freedoms: Which Charge I am ready everyday upon the Peril of my vital blood to make good againſt them, for the caſe of Lieutenant Col. <hi>Iohn Lilhurne,</hi> of Mr. <hi>Learner,</hi> of mine, &amp; of ſome others, if but duly conſidered, is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to evidence and confirme the truth then of to every common capacity, as alſo to their <hi>Prerogative Lordſhips</hi> ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſhame &amp; confuſion of face, if not to the utter extirpation of that their unlimited Arbitrary Domination and power, the which I ſhall faithfully endeavour to the utmoſt of my power for the freedome and weale of the reſt of my Nationall Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the free borne Commons of England, though in that hot and deſperate ſervice I, and mine, wife, children and all be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by their unreaſonable cruelty.</p>
               <p>Thus Sir having made my complaint unto you, and in mine, to this Honourable Committee, the complaint of the whole Commons of <hi>England,</hi> all being equally interreſted with me in this conteſt betwixt the Lords and the Commoners both in life, limb, liberty, and eſtate; I preſent my cauſe, and in mine, the cauſe of the whole Commons of <hi>England</hi> to your grave and judicious conſideration: for, looke what is done unto me or to any other (though never ſo meane or of inferiour degree) for mine or their vindication and maintenance of the juſt Rights and freedoms of the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> is as done unto the whole Commons of <hi>England,</hi> for by thoſe their inſultings all as well as one, are made lyable to the unlimited cruelty and oppreſſion of their prerogative juriſdiction. And if they may rule by prerogative, then farwell all liberty and property, all Lawes, juſtice, and equity; and if it muſt be ſo, I pray you beare us no longer in ſuſpence and expection of redreſſe, but forthwith let our Doom be proclaimed to the whole world, that the Commons of <hi>England</hi> may know what to truſt to; that we may looſe our labour no longer in petitioning, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing, complaining, and ſeeking for reliefe at your hands, that ſuch as will may ſit down as contented ſlaves with hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114013:12"/> about their necks to be hanged up till the pleaſure of that Houſe (forſooth) ſhall be further ſignified.</p>
               <p>Now Sir, I ſhall uſe no other provocations, incitations or Arguments to this Honourable Committee, to the diſcharge of their duty, but ſhall altogether leave the whole matter hereof to your conſciences, whether for juſtice or injuſtice, mercy or cruelty; for my part I care not though you and all men forſake me, ſo long as I know the Lord liveth, who will once judge every man according to his deeds, whether good or evel, and then I am ſure I ſhall have righteous judgment, withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reſpect of perſons; and againſt that, to deprive me thereof, neither the gates of Hell nor the powers of Earth are able to prevaile; that is my comfort, my hope and ſupport, againſt all afflictions cryalls, and troubles: And therefore in that ſure confidence though I be thus enthralled &amp; encompaſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry ſidewith Bands &amp; Aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ictions, I am reſolved not to yeeld an haires-bredth of ſubjection, no, not ſo much, as the appearance of ſubjection either in word or deed to any arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary power, orders, ſignifications of their pleaſures, &amp;c. <hi>maugre</hi> their Priſons, Irons, Halters, &amp;c. either for me or mine: And this I pronounce to this Honourable Committee and to the whole Commons of England in open defyance and contempt of the Arbitrary Domination of the Houſe of Peers, their uſurpation and incroachments over the Rights and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the Commons of <hi>England;</hi> come what come will, or what the utmoſt of their uſurped might and power can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict upon me for it,</p>
               <p>I ſcorne their mercy, and dare them to do their worſt: let them find Priſons, Dungeons, Irons, Halters, &amp;c. Ile find Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſſe, Neck, and Heeles, for one in contempt to their uſurped juriſdiction; for reſolved I am to break before I bend to their oppreſſions, &amp;c. Sir I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From Newgate the place of my Prerogative Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity. <date>Feb. 1. 1647.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Yours and all mens for their juſt Rights and Freedoms, faithfull, to the death. Richard Overton.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
